# Partho Biswas

#### Software Engineer - iOS

7+ years of professional experience in iOS platform, well-versed in Clean-Modular architecture, UI/UX, algorithm and data-structure. I built high performant apps, used by millions, and codebase that scales to large team of engineers, drove the product vision for my company.

Dhaka, Bangladesh +8801722455000 partho.maple@gmail.com github.com/partho-maple linkedin.com/in/partho-biswas

**WORK EXPERIENCE** 

#### iOS Software Architect/Consultant

Self-employed / Freelance

Jan, 2020 – Current Remote

- Solved 700+ algorithmic problems on different platforms (Leetcode & AlgoExpert) and read 10+ iOS books as self improvement quest
- Helped implementing complex features and architectural issues for different startups to achieve their product goals
- Contributed to open source projects like WooCommerce iOS app and created few open source projects that gained 600+ stars

iOS Software Architect

Aurea Software

Jun, 2017 - Dec, 2019

Remote, through Crossover.com

Increased the revenue by 5% for the company by delivering the Jive Daily app, leading a team of 4 developers

- Rearchitectured and developed Aurea-CRM app from Objective-C to Swift that scales to 12+ concurrent engineers with 90% Unit Testability
- Rearchitectured monolithic codebase to Clean-Modular architecture that improved startup time by 50% and build time by 70%
- Designed & developed the APIs and network layer collaborating with cross-functional teams, improving network data consumption by 20%

Senior Software Engineer (iOS)

Dhaka, Bangladesh

IPVision Canada Inc.

- Achieved  $\sim$ 5 million users, on ringID app, developed from scratch with a team of 6 engineers
- Implemented VoIP, Streaming and Store module/SDK for iOS with 95% Unit Test Coverage
- Developed custom image library that Improved image rendering quality and speed by 40% leading a team of 2 engineers
- Developed custom UI/UX components in Swift, used in multiple inhouse apps
- Improved app stability by 70% by developing custom debugging tool to troubleshoot on cross language project

Software Engineer (iOS)

Code Knight Solutions/ X-10 Technology.

Sept, 2013 - Aug, 2014

Dhaka, Bangladesh

- Developed flagship VoIP dialer app for iOS and iPad that generated \$125K revenue in it's first year
- Codeveloped inhouse VoIP SDK for SIP/SDP, audio and video codecs.
- Improved G729 codec performance by replacing arithmetic operations with bitwise operations that reduced audio latency by 20%

SKILLS

- iOS, Swift, Objective-C
- MVP, MVVM, MVVM-C, VIPER, VIP
- Unit/UI Testing (TDD, BDD)
- iOS performance tuning, App profiling
- RESTful, JSON, Websocket

- Design Patterns, SOLID, Jira, Git, Agile
- Reactive programming (RxSwift)
- Continuous Integration & Delivery
- Algorithms & Problem Solving
- UIKit, CoreData, Alamofire, AutoLayout
- C++, Python
- Audio Video streaming technologies
- WebRTC, SIP, SDP, RTP, H.264
- VOIP, Media & Network programming

NOTEWORTHY

- Ranking #1 Swift GitHub developer and #2 Objective-C GitHub developer in Bangladesh on GitHub-awards
- Solved 700+ algorithmic problems on different platforms (Leetcode.com & AlgoExpert.io). Enthusiastic competitive programmer
- Currently have 2K+ reputation and among Top 10% iOS, 20% Objective-C and 30% Swift Contributor on StackOverflow.com

**EDUCATION** 

#### Shahjalal University of Science and Technology

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science and Engineering

Sylhet, Bangladesh Feb, 2009 - May, 2013

**PROJECTS** 

ringID

Architectured and developed audio and video calling SDK, image SDK and module from planning to production.

Optimized the audio and video codecs to work on low latency and internet speed

## ringID Messenger

Proprietor: Ring Inc, concern of IPVision Canada Inc.

Proprietor: Ring Inc, concern of IPVision Canada Inc.

Implemented custom video filtering and live image rendering algorithm reducing GPU throughput by 20%

Architectured and developed audio/video calling SDK solely. Led a team of 2 developers

# Jive Daily (Product Line)

Proprietor: Jive Software, concern of Aurea Software

- Developed messaging system, facebook like newsfeed solely. Codeveloped networking, database. Contributed on almost whole app.
- Achieved 90% unit test coverage while using customized MVVM and service oriented architecture
- Managed MDM servers and configurations for MobileIron, AirWatch

## Aurea CRM.pad

Proprietor: Aurea Software

- Led the development of Aurea-CRM app from legacy MVC, Objective-C/C++ codebase to latest Swift
- Improved performance and memory usage by 30%, achieved 95% unit test coverage while using VIPER and TDD
- Developed complete Continuous Integration and Continuous Delivery pipeline.

#### **Gold Dialer**

Proprietor: Code Knight Solutions Inc.

Wrote the app solely from planning to production including VoIP SDK